<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truthe tryed very comfortable to the faithfull, but a discomfort to the enemies of God / newly sette forth by J.S.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2307</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23258818</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23258818</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truthe tryed very comfortable to the faithfull, but a discomfort to the enemies of God / newly sette forth by J.S.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Sutton for Edward Sutton dwellyng in Lumbarde strete at the signe of the cradell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Lo[n]don :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the xxi. day of December, in the yere of our Lorde 1562.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Perused and allouued according to the Quenes Maiesties iniunctions"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:1"/>
            <p>TRVTHE tryed, <hi>very comfortable to the faithfull: but a diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the enemies of God. Newly ſette forth by. I. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prouerbes.</hi> 10. <hi>Prouerbes.</hi> 11. The memoriall of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall haue a good report, but the name of the vngodlye ſhal ſtink, and their hope, ſhall periſh, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly ſhall fall in their ovvne vvickednes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:2"/>
            <head>The preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the budding branches of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good materiall tree, at their due tyme thorough the mighty worke of God, bryng forth fruite pleaſaunt and comfortable for the contentation and refreſhyng of the outwarde man: althoughe not eche branche or bough repleniſhed with lyke quantitie, So likewiſe the branches of the beautiful tree of gods eternal truth thorough hys gracious appointment, bryngeth forth ſuch fruite, as is for the comfort and ſuſtenance of the inwarde man, the ſpirituall ſoule: and thoughe euery branche be not endued with like aboundance, or repleniſhed with lyke quantitie of ſwete perſwaſions, yet not in the quantitie onelye, but as well in the qualitye, conſiſteth the vertue of eche thynge. And for as muche as we ſhall render accomptes of the talentes receyued, and therefore are admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, whether they bee fewe or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, muche or lyttell, yet dyligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to employe and beſtowe theym,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:3"/>
to the aduancement of gods glory, and the edifyeng of our chriſten brethern. I therfore as one of the vnprofitableſt vnfruitfulleſt, and moſte vnworthieſt the name of a branche of that tree, yet being deſyrous to imparte vnto others ſuche fruite as God hathe indued me with: and to employe my talent to the glorie of God, and the comforte of my bretherne: haue therefore enterpriſed this lyttell woorke, whiche althoughe not in that ſorte and order, as if it had bene touched by the handes of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet I nothyng myſtruſt, but that the gentill reader wyll conceyue the beſte of my good wylle and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. And foraſmuch as the maner of many men, when newe workes come to their handes, is, to ſatiſfie them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with readyng here &amp; there a piece, and being ſoone wearie, theyr trauaile to none effect. I haue therfore thought good to require thee gentill reader, not to thinke it troubleſome to reade and againe to rede ouer theſe ſo few leaues whiche vnto the godly mynded, ſhall be both pleaſant and comfortable: and as herein thou ſhalt perceiue the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:26461:3"/>
puniſhmentes &amp; iuſt plages which god hath in ſtore, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſgreſſors of his preceptes, and neglectours of hys wordes, to the ruine decaye and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of that people and contrey: ſo ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> lykewyſe beholde his vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable and ineſtimable benefites and bleſſynges, whyche he of his almighty mercy, moſt plentyfully and abundant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly poureth vpon that people and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where his holy and bleſſed word, with thankful hartes is embraced. Of which both) in this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d we haue had the experience, as to the reader ſhall moſt perfectlye appeare. Thus partly for the declaryng my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to God, &amp; the zeale I beare vnto his truth as alſo my harty deſyre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinual proſperous eſtate of my contrey as nature forceth me, I haue through the ſufferance and aſſiſtance of God, ſymply fyniſhed my enterpriſe begon, geuynge hym whollye the prayſe. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:4"/>
            <l>VVold god the ſmart which we for ſin,</l>
            <l>So late did worthely taſt:</l>
            <l>Might cauſe vs loth the wickednes,</l>
            <l>That now aboundes ſo faſte.</l>
            <l>That God may ſpare our ſoules from death</l>
            <l>And by his mighty power:</l>
            <l>Preſerue vs ſtill from thoſe, that ſeeke,</l>
            <l>Our freedome to deuoure.</l>
            <l>For ſure if ſtill we dwell in ſinne,</l>
            <l>And liue in careleſſenes:</l>
            <l>Such wofull plages ſhall ſoone enſue,</l>
            <l>As I cannot expreſſe.</l>
            <l>Be warned in time, and feare the lord,</l>
            <l>And with pure myndes and heartes:</l>
            <l>Embrace gods truth, folowe the ſame:</l>
            <l>Such are the chriſtians partes.</l>
            <l>Then thoſe which yet his truth reſiſte,</l>
            <l>God ſhall iuſtly rewarde:</l>
            <l>That neither of the lorde, nor yet,</l>
            <l>of ſoueraigne haue regarde.</l>
            <l>But ſtubburnly againſt the lawe,</l>
            <l>of God and Quene contende:</l>
            <l>Whoſe wylful wickednes at laſt,</l>
            <l>Shall worke their woful ende.</l>
            <l>And ſuche as feare the lorde their God,</l>
            <l>Shal certainly be bleſt:</l>
            <l>And ſhall after this life enioye,</l>
            <l>In heauen eternall reſt.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Truth tryed, very comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to the faithfull: but a diſcomfort to the enemies of god. New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſette forth by. I. S. <hi>1562.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auyng zelouſly waied &amp; conſidered the great benefite and bleſſing, that god of his infinite mercy, hath againe ſo louingly and merciful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beſtowed vpon vs, his people of England, me thoughte I ſay my ſelf of duety forced euen for con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, to ſtirre vp the myndes of others my brethren, by puttyng them in remembraunce of the ſame, leaſt we agayne neglectyng and beyng forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of oure bounden duetye towardes god, our heauenly father in this behalf ſhoulde woorthely feele a greater and more greuous ſmarte and plage then that, which we alreadye thorough our late frailtye and forgetfulnes haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of: call therfore to mynde my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne, howe that of longe and manye yeares before the lighte of the Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:26461:5"/>
appered, and ſhyned amongſt vs here in Englande, bothe we and oure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were ſeduced, walkyng blyndly in darknes, and in ſtraye pathes lyke loſte ſhepe, without theyr ſhepherde, we were nouryſhed, fedde, and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered vp with fooliſhe fantaſies and dotynge dreames of mans inuention with trifles, I ſay, were we trayned in the broade pathes that led to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, drawne by the guydes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, deſtroyers as much as in them is, both of body and ſoule: Oh cankred caterpyllers thoroughe whoſe ſubtill meanes &amp; diueliſhe deluſions we were ſo blynded, that we neither knew god nor howe to walke in his holy ways: but ſtyll kept ignorant from all godly knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding. It wold be to tedious to make here a reherſall of the whole number of the not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie and nedeleſſe ceremonies, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the peuyſhnes of Balams balde ones: and therfore I wil not but only treate a lyttell of the woful wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippyng of ymages, and the deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maſſe (whych bothe) they myghtily maintained, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:5"/>
as manifeſtly ſhall appere.</p>
            <p>And fyrſte, howe greuouſly offended we the maieſtie of the almighty God, takyng from hym the honor onely due vnto hym, and geuynge the ſame to carued, grauen, and molten ymages,<note place="margin">Pſalm 135.</note> and ydols, hauing mouths and ſpeake not, eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not, neither hauing any breath in their mouthes, being but ſtocks and ſtones, the workes of mens handes: and yet howe wickedly worſhipped we them, runnyng and gaddyng on pilgremage to them to make amendes for our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lyfe, ſekyng at their hands remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins: which is no where to be ſought nor had, but at the hands of god only: as witneſſeth the Euangeliſt Marke, Who (ſayeth he) can forgeue ſynnes,<note place="margin">Mar. 2. Math. 9. Iohn. 24. Act. 4.</note> but God only? Chriſt is the way, truth and lyfe, no man cometh vnto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but by hym, neyther is there ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion in any other, nor yet is there any other name geuen vnto men, wherein we muſt be ſaued, but the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt: and yet not withſtandynge, (we) then deſtitute of this godly know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtandynge, wandred
<pb facs="tcp:26461:6"/>
from place to place, from countrey to countrey, to offer, to cary and bryng to them that neyther, ſawe nor felte, but yet receauers they had that refuſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: al was fyſhe that came to the net with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: theſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>feryng pilgrimages had that papiſticall broode &amp; Romyſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able deuiſed for their own lukers ſake which though beneficiall to themſelues yet moſte abhominable in the ſighte of God, and a playne robbyng of God of the honour and reuerence only due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym: wherof thoughe they were not ignoraunt, yet careles.</p>
            <p>Secondly, touching the Maſſe which was their chiefe ſtaffe to ſtand by, howe were we by them perſuaded, coniured, and brought to beleue the ſame to be a ſacrifice, to put away the ſinnes, bothe of the quicke and the dead: and that by the vertue ther of (as they ſaide) they tranſported ſoules from purgatorye to paradiſe, purchaſed eternall ſaluation: ye, what ſore was it not a ſalue for? or what diſeaſes wold it not cure? And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the wordes of conſecration ſpoken, then no bread nor wine to remaine, but were forthwith altered and turned into
<pb facs="tcp:26461:6"/>
the very body and bloude of Chriſte, ye the very ſame proportion of body that honge on the croſſe, to be there foorthe commyng at their commaundemente: they had hym in a ſtrynge in ſuche ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, to plucke him to them, and put him from them, at their owne pleaſure: the creator to be ſubiect to the creature. Oh abhominable blaſphemye, oh diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe deteſtable and ſhameleſſe ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, directly denying the death of Ieſu Chriſte to be onely ſufficient. But now beholde therefore what they are, and what theyr owne doyngs declare them to be, euen the very enemyes of Chriſt Ieſu: they kepte the ſymple ones igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte, and ſhewe themſelues to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen they,<note place="margin">Ro. xvi.</note> whome Paule willed vs to be ware of, who with their flatteryng woordes, and ſweete preachynges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the heartes of the innocentes: Theſe I ſaye be they, of that viperous generation, of that fylthye broode, that oure Sauiour Chriſt warneth vs of,<note place="margin">Math 24. Mar. xiii.</note> by the holy Euangeliſt Mathew. * If any man ſay vnto you, to here is Chriſte, or there is Chriſte, beleue them not. For there ſhall aryſe falſe Chriſtes, and
<pb facs="tcp:26461:7"/>
fals prophets ſhal do great myracles &amp; wonders: in ſo much that if it wer poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very elect ſhold be deceiued. And alas howe were we poore ſelye wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and innocentes in bondage wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly wrapped in captiuitie, of many yeares ſubiect to theſe gredy whelpes of Antichriſt who without all ſhame and deſtitute of godly feare, continual lye poured out vppon, and in maner drouned vs with innumerable blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies and hipocritical ſuperſtitious ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies ageinſt God and his truthe. Thus were we by them led towardes deſtruction of body and ſoule: Thus were we through that wicked Romiſh trayne ſtill kepte from the bryght bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of gods holy worde.</p>
            <p>And beyng thus in our chiefe extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie at an exigent, euen at the pytte brynke of pardition, beholde the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull goodnes of our almyghty God, the God of our forefathers, Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob: beholde (I ſay) the great care of God for his people: who he ſo derely hath bought euen with the precious bloude of his ſonne Chriſte: behold how God here tendred the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes
<pb facs="tcp:26461:7"/>
of his owne handes: ye and behold the ſweete and comfortable promyſes of our ſauiour Chriſte: moſte louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed. Nothyng (ſaith he) is in ſecrete, that ſhall not come abrode,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.</note> nor any thyng hyd that ſhall not come to light &amp; be know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For loſt pleſed our heauenly father of his free mercy then that his worde ſhould be a lanterne to our feete,<note place="margin">Pſal 119. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and a lyght to our path wais where as before we walked in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, now dyd the blynde ſee, and the deafe heare: and to the poore was the gladde tidyngs preached:<note place="margin">Pſalm 19.</note> This woord gaue lyght and brought foorth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding euen vnto the very babes, it offred an euerlaſting enheritance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thoſe that with conſtaunt faithe did or doo imbrace it. God ſtirred vp then his faithful miniſters to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the ſame his wil vnto vs,<note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> to winne his people vnto hymſelfe: Oh how merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully dyd god then bleſſe vs, and ſhew the light of his countenance vpon vs, geuyng vs true and ſkilful ſhepardes to guide vs, euen ſuch as at his hands had receiued a ſpiritual vnderſtanding They preached vnto vs the kyngdome
<pb facs="tcp:26461:8"/>
of god to be at hand. They preached vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſt ſhepe of Iſrael, the goſpel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of god. They preached repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance,<note place="margin">Mathe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> * Freely they receyued eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the good gyfte of god: And freely they gaue agayn: ſo that thorough the ſounde and true doctrine of Ieſu Chriſt taught by them, we were led to the ſtrayght and narrowe waye that leadeth vnto lyfe.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> Note therfore nowe, gentyl Chriſtian, the great diuerſitie in this pointe, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the fantaſies, dreames, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of the perillous papiſtes, and how much they varye and diſagre with the truth of god taught vnto vs by the faythfull miniſters of his moſt holy and inuincible worde. The Romiſh broode taught vs, that with gadding on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and offring of money and trifles to ſtockes and blockes, our ſinnes were forgeuen vs, and that thoſe worme ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ambaſſadours, and painted Idoles, were as mediators to take vp the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter betwene god and vs: but S. Iames ſayeth,<note place="margin">Iames. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that theſe bee lyers againſt the truth, and their wiſedom not to diſcend from aboue, but is earthly, naturall, &amp; diueliſh, and therfore to be deteſted, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:8"/>
and vtterlye deſpiſed. But the true pilgremage in dede was taughte vs by the truſtye meſſangers of their Maſter Chriſt.<note place="margin">Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 2.</note> And which (of al Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans) ought continually to be obſerued and followed: and this it is,<note place="margin">Iame, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that we ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtayn from ſleſhely luſtes, which fyght agaynſt the ſoule, to viſit the priſoners and ſuccourles people, the fatherleſſe in their aduerſity: to clothe, and couer our nedy naked brethren with ſom holſom and comfortable garment. &amp;c. But not to apparrell the blunt blocke, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feeleth heate nor colde. and howe is it then poſſible they ſhoulde help vs, or do vs any pleaſure, that cannot helpe themſelues? ye what neede we anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mediatour or interceſſour,<note place="margin">Iohn, i.</note> but him whome we haue alreadye to be our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate with the father euen Ieſu Chriſt that righteous one. And thus dydde thoſe holy men of God teache vs, they taughte vs, Chriſt alone to be oure in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terceſſour and aduocate: and that God alone, abſolueth and freelye forgeueth vs for Chriſt his ſake all our ſins, if we earneſtly repent and beleue, as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Peter: we are ſaith he,<note place="margin">1. Peter 1</note> iuſtified by
<pb facs="tcp:26461:9"/>
faithe only in Chriſt his blood: let this be ſufficient in this pointe.</p>
            <p>And now to the ſecond pointe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the reall preſence of Chriſt to be in their Maſſe, whiche the Papiſtes continually taught earneſtly affirmed and with tooth and nayle mainteined. Note now I ſay here, the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thereof taught vs by Chriſt his miniſters, which they lerned in the boke of life, vppon whiche foundation the apoſtles and auncient fathers and doctours of the Church in this pointe haue builded as vpon a moſt ſure and infallible rocke,<note place="margin">Hebr. ix. Act. 7.17. Eſay. 66.</note> Chriſte (ſaith Paule) is not entred into the holy places that are made with handes, whiche are but ſimilitudes of true thynges, but is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the very heauens for to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare now in the ſight of God for vs. Euery prieſt is ready daily miniſtring and oftentymes offreth one maner of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frynge,<note place="margin">Hebr. x.</note> whiche can neuer take awaye ſynne: but this man after he had offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one ſacrifice for ſynnes, ſatte hym downe for euer on the right hande of God, and from henſfoorth taryeth till his foes be made his footeſtoole. Ye
<pb facs="tcp:26461:9"/>
ſhal haue poore folke always with you,<note place="margin">Math. 26. Iohn 12. Mark. 14. Iohn. 7.</note> but me ſhall ye not haue. Alſo Sainte Iohn in hys vii. Chapiter, ye ſhall ſeke me, and ſhal not fynde me: wher I am, thether can ye not come. Athanaſius likewiſe in his crede ſayth, that Chriſt aſcended into heauen, and ſytteth on the ryghte hande of God, the father almyghtie: from whence he ſhall come to Iudge the quicke and the dead. And more ouer in the articles of oure fayth, the thyrde daye he roſe agayne from the dead, he aſcended into heauen, and ſytteth on the righte hande of God, and from thence (he ſhal come to Iudge the quicke and the dead:) which iudgement of the quicke and the dead, if it be alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſt, then is Chriſt really preſent, as the papyſtes affyrme: But if that dred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful day be yet to com, (as it is the part &amp; duty of Chriſtians to beleue,) although it be not farre of, then is not Chriſt now with vs, as in hys humanitye,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. Marce. 8. Luc. 9.</note> but (ſhal come) in the glorye of hys father, with hys Angels, and then ſhall reward eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordyng to his dedes: at whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng God graunt we may be found readye and not ſlepyng. Wel then for
<pb facs="tcp:26461:10"/>
as muche as that one offrynge of Ieſu Chriſt being all in al, and onely ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: To what entent or purpoſe ſhould we haue ſuch &amp; ſo many daily ſacrifices? for what are they but a very plain deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Chriſt crucifyed, to be a ſacrifyce only ſufficient for thoſe, that beleue to haue ſaluation therby? And thus good Chriſtian brethren, although ther be in holy ſcripture many more places to bee alledged, which myght be applyed, and aptly ſerue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatyſfyeng o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an conſciences in this point, that Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of the father, as touchyng hys humanitye: Yet I praye you, let theſe for briefnes preſently bee ſufficiente, and hereby may ye now ſee how the iugglyng Maſſe Prieſts haue abuſed the Sacrament of the body and bloude of Chriſt, whiche myſtery of all the faythfull, oughte thus to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded: and for this purpoſe did Chriſt our ſauior inſtitute, ordaine, and leaue it vnto vs to be vſed.</p>
            <p>That thou Chriſtian, ſhouldeſt come there vnto, with a penitent hart, for thy former offences, fullye and earneſtlye purpoſyng through the aſſiſtance of the
<pb facs="tcp:26461:10"/>
almighty, to put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, the new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is created after god in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and holynes of truth, &amp; ſtedfaſtlye beleuynge, that through the paſſion, bloudſhed, and death of Chriſt, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe, which the bread &amp; wyne as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignes do repreſent, thou haſt, I ſay, obtayned full remyſſion of thy ſynnes. And in thys fayth, with reuerence and humblenes of hart, eate and drynke the myſteries of the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt. And this glorious worke hath oure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye and gratious God the father, wrought in &amp; by his ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, our ſauiour, for the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of as many as ſtedfaſtly beleue the ſame. And thus is to be vnderſtanded of this pure &amp; holy Sacrament: and not that after the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl ſorcerye and coniuration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt, being finiſhed, the bodye of oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſte to be forth with there, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful proportion of hys humanitye. For as Sainte Auſten witneſſeth, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily preſence of Chriſte, (concerninge his humanitye) is in ſome one place of heauen, but hys diuyne preſence was, is, and ſhalbe there, here, and in all places, where it ſhal pleaſe, hym,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:11"/>
alwaies ready to aſſiſte thoſe that fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully ar gathered together in his name. And agayne he ſayeth, as concernyng the preſence of hys fleſhe, The Church had Chriſt but a fewe dayes, yet nowe it holdeth hym faſte by fayth, though it ſee hym not with eyes. Cirillus, lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe wryteth, that all thoughe Chriſte toke awaye from hence the preſence of his body, yet in the Maieſty of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heade, he is euer here. Alſo Gregory af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that Chriſt is not here by the preſence of hys fleſhe, and yet is abſent no where by the preſence of hys Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye: And thys I take to be ſo playnly ſayd, to ſatyſfye in thys poynt, as that there nedeth no more rehearſall of any other authors: But if thys ſuffyſe the not, reſorte then vnto the golden booke of that worthye Cramner, late Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhoppe of Canturburye, where thou mayeſt haue grounde woorke and ſure foundation ſufficient to buyld thy faith vpon in thys poynt: and then with an vpryght conſcience iudge indyfferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, howe muche the dyueliſhe and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious doctrine inuented by the papiſts, dyſagreeth and varyeth from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb facs="tcp:26461:11"/>
woorde of God, and the opinions and mynds of the fathers, and the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the primatiue church. Wel thus were we inſtructed: thus had we (I ſay) the truth of god taught and opened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: we were dayly fed and nouriſhed with the liuely words of god. In the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forth and teachyng wherof, when the preachers had diligently traueled, and through their zelous earneſtnes in the declaration of their Maſter Chriſt hys meſſage they had ſo inſtructed and taught vs, that thereby we were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what trayned from the daungerous &amp; perillous pathwaies of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we were before blyndly led: and that by the aſſiſtance of God through thoſe hys miniſters wee were broughte to ſome vnderſtandyng and knowledge of hym, and hadde ſome taſte and ſwete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Goſpell of Ieſu Chriſte, which is the pleaſaunt path way, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to eternall ſaluation: Then ſeaſed they not but continually and louyngly exhorted vs, not to bee forgetfull of the greate mercye that God hadde ſo louynglye ſhewed in the reuealynge of hys truthe vnto vs, ſtyl puttyng vs
<pb facs="tcp:26461:12"/>
in remembrance to perſeuer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame,<note place="margin">Proue 23,</note> applying our hartes vnto learning, and our eares vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of knowledge,<note place="margin">2, Timo, 3,</note> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in reading y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, which is able to make vs wiſe vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, throughe the fayth whiche is in Chriſt Ieſu. Thus wer we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taught, ye infinite numbers of godly inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs by theſe ſchoole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters worthy of their office:<note place="margin">1, Peter, 2</note> Theſe wer true inſtructors, theſe were they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaketh of, euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true prophets of the choſen generation of the holy natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; peculiar people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhewed vs the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of him, that called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into his marueylous lyght, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great mercy of God &amp; their paynful trauel, induſtrye, &amp; dayly preaching, we were trayned, &amp; accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame a whyle we walked. Alas, in dede but a whyle, for al to ſoone we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be weary of our welfare: we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned wel doing, &amp; waxed forgetful of the great goodnes of almyghty god to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs: we were vnthankefull, for the great benefites, receaued at his hands, we herkened not diligently to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God, pronounced by his meſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:12"/>
but necglected our duties, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God and hys myniſters: &amp; yet not withſtandyng our peruers careleſneſſe then, ſuch was the pity &amp; mercy of God (tendering vs as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would not ſodenly, ſo ſharply deale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, as our deſertes deſerued, for ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regarding ſo worthy a Iuel (his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly woorde) but rather louyngly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs by the mouthes of his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; choſen veſſels, to kepe vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould not fal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym. They, I ſay, cryed out to vs for the amendment of our lyfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould leaue of ſynne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and follow vertue, that we ſhold remember the great mercye &amp; wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful worke of god, in reueling his truth vnto vs. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould with earneſt and zelous hartes embrace it: &amp; whyle we had the light, to beleue in the light, that we might be the children of lyght, leaſt darknes again ouerwhelmed vs. Thus were we then daily taught, and put in remembraunce: Feruente was the loue of Goddes worde in theſe hys choſen, and carefull were theſe ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardes, for the flock committed to their charge: but careles we were, &amp; coldly
<pb facs="tcp:26461:13"/>
affected, nothyng regarding or paſſing for their godly admonitions and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: which our careleſnes when they perceiued, and that gentle and louyng perſuaſions woulde not preuaile, then thundred they oute the plages, whiche god had prepared, being then euen at hande for vs: and wherof we might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure oure ſelues, vnleſſe ſpedye repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and amendment of oure former wickednes and diſſolute lyfe. And was it not then preached, and daily by them cryed out in our eares, that if we wold not hearken vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced vnto vs by his miniſters, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> obedient heartes walke accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame,<note place="margin">Deu 28.4</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then we ſhould go waſt, and be made an enſaumple &amp; a ieſting ſtock to all nacions? Ye was it not by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt certainly ſaide, that if we continued in our vnthankfulnes, God woulde geue vs into the handes and gouernment of a forraine prince:<note place="margin">Deute 28 Ieremy 5 Barn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 4,</note> and that god woulde bryng a natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon vs from far, whoſe tongue we ſhold not vnderſtand, which ſhold neither regard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde, nor haue compaſſion on the young? Did they not threaten vs in the name of the
<pb facs="tcp:26461:13"/>
lord with ſworde, hunger, &amp; peſtilence, if we conſidered not the great bleſſings of god, beyng thankefull for the ſame: and framed our lyues according to hys goſpell?<note place="margin">Amos, 8</note> Did they not with Amos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of the hunger of the worde of god to come vpon vs, and that we ſhould go from ſea to ſea, and from the South to the Eaſt to ſeeke it, and ſhould not find it? were not theſe terrible threatninges dailye preached and pronounced vnto vs, the rather to moue and ſtirre oure heartes and myndes to loue &amp; embrace gods truthe, and the better to conſider the louyng kyndnes of God towardes vs? But alas, all would not helpe, the gentle perſuaſions, the terrible threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyngs, as wel the one as the other wer in vayne. So much were we with care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes corrupt, wallowing in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſo fylthelye infected with vyce, ſo much contemnyng ſpirituall inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo luſtyng after carnall thynges of this worlde, ſo addicte to our own wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſo puft vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pryde, ſo little brother<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly loue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs, ſo altogether care leſſe, that we neither regarde God nor his miniſters: we were not obedient to
<pb facs="tcp:26461:14"/>
the voice of our teachers,<note place="margin">Pro 5.</note> nor harkened not vnto them that informed vs: The warnyng of the Prophets we toke but for wynd,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> * we were the ſeruauntes of ſynne, and did not obey with harte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the forme of doctryne, whereunto we were deliuered: we were hearers of the worde, but not doers, we deceyued our ſelues:<note place="margin">Iames 1.</note> for he that heareth the word and doth it not, is like vnto a man that beholdeth his bodelye face in a glaſſe: for as ſoone as he hathe looked vppon hym ſelfe, he forgetteth foorthewith what his faſhion was: but happye is the hearer and that dothe folowe: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we dydde not but wholy neglected, and therefore dyd kyndle the wrathe of the lorde againſt vs: And the lord then hydyng his face and ſwete countenance from vs, perfourmed his promiſe, and iuſtelye poured vppon vs the plages wherewyth he puniſheth thoſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeye his godlye wyll, and tranſgreſſe his holye lawe and commaundements. For did not then the king of glorye and power, whoſe heauye wrathe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our peruerſnes we had purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſodenly take from vs our noble and
<pb facs="tcp:26461:14"/>
prudent prince king Edward the vi. ſo worthye an ympe, ſo vertuous, ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, ſo gratiouſly grounded in chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, ſo altogether geuen to aduaunce and ſet forth the glory of god, as that the like of him in godly ſkil, and of ſo tender yeares, the earthe didde not conteyne: The lyuyng god had ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, endued and ſo plenteouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed his princely harte with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and heauenly vnderſtanding, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had made him more meeter to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite the holy heauens, there to he hold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mighty maieſty of god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to continue on this corrupt erth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs wicked wretches, that liued in ſecurity &amp; waxed forgetful of the great benefits and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable bleſſings of our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And therfore did god take from vs our ſo ioiful a iuel, our pereles prince, &amp; with him the word of life, the ſwete &amp; comfortable goſpel of Ieſu Chriſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che nouriſhed and was the pretious pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruatiue of our ſoules: And for our vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes ſuffred vs again to be made dronke with the ſpirite of error: and as the lotheſome dogge to his vomyte, or the filthy ſow to her wallowing in the
<pb facs="tcp:26461:15"/>
myre, ſo were we turned agayne to our olde abhominations: we worſhipped i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles, we ſerued ſtraunge gods of wood and ſtone, we did the workes of the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then, whereby we highlye offended the maieſty of the almightie: who therefore gaue vs ouer into the hands &amp; gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a ſtraunge king and nation, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording as he promiſed by the mouth of Ieremy,<note place="margin">Ierem, 8,</note> * ſayinge: I will geue theyr wines vnto aleantes, and their fieldes to deſtroyers, and ſo it came to paſſe: for they who vtterlye hated vs, reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs: we were ſubiect, I ſaye, vnto a nation fully infected with filthy idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and all abhominations of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſuperſtitious hipocriſy, (a nation) with whome for their preſumption and pride, not Lucifer him ſelfe in his chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt arrogancye might compare: a viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people, which daily deuoured both wiues and widowes, &amp; defloured may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, a broode of caterpillers, that waſt conſume, and deſtroye all where they come, a merciles people, and deſtitute of the true knowledge of god. What ſhould I ſay, euen a people, hated and abhorred of vs, and of all nations: And
<pb facs="tcp:26461:15"/>
yet we wer then in ſubiection to them:<note place="margin">Pſalm, 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world turned vp ſide down with Englande, mercy and pitye were fled the realm, and merciles cruelty ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plied the place, iniquitie had the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand. The true teachers and preachers of his worde, the miniſters and choſen veſſels of Ieſu Chriſt,<note place="margin">i, Cori. 4. i. Theſſa. 2</note> were then made as it had bene gaſyng ſtockes to all the worlde, reuiled, euil ſpoken of, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, empriſoned, and that onely for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing their maiſter Chriſt: but happy ye twiſe happye are they and all ſuche, for the ſpirite of god,<note place="margin">i, Peter. 4,</note> and the ſpirite of glory reſteth vpon them, that he railed vpon for the name of Chriſt. For ſuche as God hathe choſen to himſelfe, haue bene in reſpect of the world, wretched miſerable, turmoiled with manifolde troubles: for ſo is the promiſe of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightye God,<note place="margin">Iohn 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> * Becauſe ye bee not of the worlde, the worlde doth hate you, and all that will liue godly in Chriſte Ieſu (ſaieth Paule) ſhall ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. Let therfore the fruites of the late godly miniſters, ſhewe of whence they were. For ſuche was I ſay, their ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes in Chriſte Ieſu, and ſuche was
<pb facs="tcp:26461:16"/>
their feruente zeale, loue, and hartye affection towarde GOD, and hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye worde: which they ſo perfectly prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched, and faithfully taught, that for the aduauncement thereof, and the better ſtrengthning of the faithe of their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker bretherne,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> they were content like conſtant, faithfull, and worthy ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of Ieſu Chriſte theyr graunde ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitayn, not only to ſuffer hunger, cold, railing, mocking, buffeting, whipping, and impriſoning: but alſo to geue their body to the fire, there to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed to aſhes. Oh terrible tyme, Oh pitifull ſpoile, and Oh miſerable murder &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of gods houſhold.<note place="margin">i. Peter, 2,</note> * but then was the time come, that iudgement muſt begin at the houſe of god:<note place="margin">2, Tim, 2,</note> * They wer veſſels ſanctified vnto honor mete for the lorde. This didde they through the aſſiſtaunce of the holye ghoſte, for the aduauncement of gods glory,<note place="margin">2, Tim, 2,</note> * and for the electes ſake, that they might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo obtayne the ſaluation whiche is in Chriſt Ieſu with eternall glorye: pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlye and meekely, as lambes recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued they deathe,<note place="margin">Saplen. 5,</note> * Whoſe lyfe of the
<pb facs="tcp:26461:16"/>
foolyſhe was thought to be verye mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and their ende to bee without ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour: but they are coumpted amongeſt the children of God,<note place="margin">Hebr, vi,</note> and theyr portion is amongeſt the Saintes. * Thoughe in the ſyght of the vnwyſe, they appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to dye, and theyr ende to bee verye deſtruction: yet are they in reſte, and their hope full of immortality.<note place="margin">Rom, 8, 2, Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.5 Hebr, xi,</note> * They confeſſed theymſelues to bee as ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and pylgrems vppon the earthe. They were no gredye gapers for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermente, neyther benefice, nor Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryke, nor anye other worldlye promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or dignitye: although largelye of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred and promiſed (yf they would haue forſaken their maiſter Chriſte, and hys woorde) coulde tempte or ouercome theym, nor with drawe theyr earneſte myndes from God: They woulde not be fedde with eye pleaſures, they eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not the tryſlyng treaſure of thys tranſitorye worlde, nor the vayne and peryllous pompe thereof, as the vayneglorious beallye god Byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and woorrieng wolues, who then ſucked theyr innocente bloude, dydde:
<pb facs="tcp:26461:17"/>
but ſuche was the godly conſtantneſſe I ſaye, of thoſe lambes of God, that they were nothynge myndefull of the countrye, wherein they then were, but were deſyrous of a better, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Sapie. 3.</note> a heauenly*. For God had proued them, and founde them mete for hym ſelfe: As golde in the furnace hadde he tryed them: * They wer led by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> bycauſe the ſpirite of God dwelled in them*: Wherefore God is not aſhamed of them, euen to be called their God, and hath prepared for them a citye, euen the heauenly Ieruſalem. Now is the promyſe of Chriſt perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in them:<note place="margin">Iames. 1.</note> * he that endureth, when he is tryed, ſhall receaue the crowne of lyfe, prepared for them that loue him, whereof they are nowe partakers. for he that looſeth his life for my ſake, ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 19.</note> ſhal fynde it: euen theſe therfore were of that number that haue geuen their lyfe for their Maſter Chriſte hys ſake, and in the defence of hys truth: therfore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue they receaued the reward of a Prophete, whiche was encreaſe of knowledge in this life, and euerlaſting ioye and felicitye in the worlde to come
<pb facs="tcp:26461:17"/>
wherof God for his mercies ſake, make vs with them to be partakers.</p>
            <p>But Oh England, be myndful how God then of hys iuſte iuſtice, reuenged the vnmercifull perſecution, &amp; bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of thoſe his innocent lambes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Martyrs, &amp; ſanctifyed ſoldiours, whoſe bloud cried vengeance in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of god, vpon the vnthankefulnes of his wycked enemyes, whiche euen then fel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, &amp; our countrey: what numbers of plages, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> followed one in an others necke, myſery dayly increaſed, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth went to ruine for want of thoſe, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the feare of god was graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed: who being alreadye murdered, or for conſcience ſake, fled their countrey, or remayning at home, abſented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to auoide the daunger of being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to death by fyre. But in a myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme, where the guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the flocke are withoute vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng, and wher the truth of God is not taught. Whereof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> experience was then bothe to well ſeene and felte: for whoe in thoſe dayes were they that flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, or whoe as the tearme goeth, ruled then the roſte, in eccleſiaſticall
<pb facs="tcp:26461:18"/>
cauſes? But the Romyſh race of prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke prelates, the monſterous mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd men, whoſe ruffle and rauenous procedynges, for wante of Godlye ſkyll, or throughe a dyuelyſhe obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, for lacke of good will to guyde theyr flocke, what Chriſtian harte la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth not to remember? For in place of true teachers of the gladde tydinges of Ieſu Chriſt, we hadde deteſtable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers, poyſoned peruerters, and ſhameleſſe ſhadowers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: whoſe onely care, ſtudye, and trauell, tended to trayne vs vp, and kepe vs in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and blyndnes, accordyng to their wonted maner, to kepe and mayntaine in full force, the whole rable of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſhe abhominations, to exalte and kepe in hys pompe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> monſterous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt of Rome, as chiefe and ſupreme head &amp; gouernour of the Church: which title by the autoritye of the Scriptures belongeth to euery prince, within his owne dominions, as well in cauſes eccleſiaſticall as temporall, and yet wer not they eyther aſhamed, or afrayed of thys theyr wicked procedynges, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpected they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of almyghty
<pb facs="tcp:26461:18"/>
God, nor regarded their due obedience to their prince: wherfore they declared themſelues to be the ſame,<note place="margin">Ierem, 5, 1, Reg, 14</note> that Ieremy ſpeaketh of: Wyſe to do euill, but to do wel, they knowe not: * ſhewinge them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues as rebellious ſorcerers, and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne wicked Idolatrers, charmers, &amp; councelers with ſpirites: they are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as in Deuteronomi is mentioned,<note place="margin">Deute, 18</note> euen all corrupt, and made abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their ſtudyes: they be euen they, through whoſe inchauntmentes,<note place="margin">Apoc, 18.</note> al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were deceaued. They left the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God,<note place="margin">Mark, 15,</note> and maintained their own conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, they made deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; gaue occaſion of euill,<note place="margin">Rom, 16,</note> contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue learned. Theſe be thoſe hipocrits y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> market places,<note place="margin">Mat, 23,</note> which deuoure widows houſes, vnder pretence of long prayer: they appeare beautiful outwards, but inward, are ful of fylthye hipocriſy and iniquitye: They deale with lyes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Ieremye: Neuertheleſſe they heale the hurte of the people very frendlye,<note place="margin">Ieremy 8,</note> ſaying, peace, peace, where there is no peace at all: Fye for ſhame ſayeth the Prophete, howe abhominable thyngs,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:19"/>
doe they,<note place="margin">Ieremi. 9</note> and yet they be not aſhamed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They bende their tonges lyke bowes to ſhoote oute lyes, and take greate paynes to doe myſchiefe: they are a deceatfull people, whiche for very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyng falſeſhod will not know me, (ſayeth the Lorde:) With their mouthe they ſpeake peaceablye to their neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, but preuily they lay wayte for him: Oh Ieremy, how truly is thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy fulfylled? what great and cruell ſmarte, and torment haue the people of god ſuffered by the meanes of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation,<note place="margin">2, Pete<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2,</note> * being themſelues the bryngers in of damnable ſectes, decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and begylers of ſtable ſoules: and throughe theyr couetouſneſſe, make marchaundyſe of Goddes people, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſyng libertye, and they themſelues the bonde ſlaues of corruption. Theſe bee the preſumptuous ſtubborne ones, that feare not to murmure, ſpeake yll of,<note place="margin">Epiſtle, Iudas.</note> and deſpyſe the hyer power *. Theſe are of thoſe vngodly that were craftyly crepte in, that tourne the grace of God vnto wantonneſſe, that denye God to be the onely Lorde Ieſu Chriſte. Wo bee vnto them: for they haue followed
<pb facs="tcp:26461:19"/>
the waye of Cayne,<note place="margin">Geneſ 4 Num, 16.</note> and are vtterly ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the errour of Balam for lukers ſake, &amp; peryſhe in the treaſon of Chore: * They are cloudes withoute water,<note place="margin">Epiſtle Iudas.</note> caryed aboute of wyndes, trees with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute fruite at gatheryng tyme, twyſe dead, and plucked vp by the rootes: they are the ragyng wolues of the ſea, fomyng oute their owne ſhame, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge ſtarres to whome is reſerued the myſtes of darkeneſſe for euer. Oh howe lyuely and perfectely hathe oure almyghtye God, by the mouthe of hys Apoſtles and Prophetes, paynted oute in theyr colours the wycked, deceatful, and deteſtable nature of thys vyperous generation &amp; bloudye broode:<note place="margin">Mat, 23,</note> at whoſe handes ſhalbe requyred the bloude of all the Prophettes, whiche was ſhed from the begynnyng of the worlde:<note place="margin">Marc 22,</note> * woe vnto them therefore, they ſhall receaue greater damnation, ſo wycked and dyuelyſhe were all theyr imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deuyſes in all theyr peſtilent procedynges, that what proſpered whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ruled: Yea was not the realme a very wilderneſſe in reſpecte of that it hadde bene before, when the Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:26461:20"/>
of Ieſu Chriſt was preached? What calamitye, what miſerye, what ſcarſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye? was not akornes in ſteade of bread a foode to a number of our poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in ſundry places in Englande? Yea howe pityfully and myſerablye, dyd numbers bothe olde and yonge dye in the ſtreates for wante of ſuſtenance? Oh lamentable chaunge and alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Whoe then ſawe not in place of plentye and aboundaunce, dearth and ſkarſenes, for healthe, ſyckeneſſe? Yea numbers of vnknowen dyſeaſes: For peace and quietnes, whiche not longe before wee quietly enioyed, dyſcention and warre, not a little hurtful bothe to people and realme: and throughe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne, ſyckenes, and warre, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and grewe fewe in number, bicauſe we herkened not vnto the voice of the Lord our God:<note place="margin">Deut. 28</note> the blockehouſes and bulwarkes whyche ſhoulde haue bene a defence to vs, and oure country, were ſpoyled, plucked downe, and raced: oure realme defaced, and made readye as a praye for oure enemyes, who dayly gaped for the ſpoyle. And
<pb facs="tcp:26461:20"/>
howe ſodenlye were wee dyſpoſſeſſed of Caliyſe? For the whiche there hadde bene diuerſe and ſundrye ſecrete at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes before, but neuer coulde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle till then, and that throughe the ſecrete treaſon of ſome arche enemye of God, more ſkylfull to kepe the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of ſelye Martyrs bound in chaines at a ſtake, enuironed with fyrye fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottes, then with a whyte ſticke in his hand to ſauegarde ſo worthye a towne agaynſte the force of the armed ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour. But (Oh Englande) neuer dyddeſt thou, nor ſhalte vnderſtande all the priuye conſpiracies and ſecret trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that by that trayterous trayne &amp; Romiſhe retinue hath ben wrought, ſo ſubtyll are they in theyr generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But nowe was England brought to thys poynte, that where as before it was hadde in eſtimation, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of forreyne enemyes, than was it in feare it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſalm, 9,</note> and was become a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſtocke to al nations. Nowe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my brethern, whether theſe were plages whiche we had worthyly deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and we at that tyme a wretched &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26461:21"/>
miſerable people, in pitifull eſtate and wofull caſe or not, I referre it to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thoſe, that either were partakers of the ſmart in that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous and daungerous tyme, or that ſaw the miſery and beheld the terrors, which being ſo few yeares paſt, I truſt be not, or I would were not forgoten: but through theſe plagues whiche we thus felt, and wherwith god long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had threatned vs by the mouth of his ſeruantes, the late perſecuted mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: Herein I ſay, dyd he declare them to be true prophets. For what thing in thoſe days hapned vnto vs, as a ſcurge and puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for our vnthankfulnes and careleſſe liuyng, that was not by thoſe the elect miniſters of Ieſu Chriſt in their lyfe tyme,<note place="margin">Deute, 18</note> declared vnto vs, ſhoulde come. Therefore were they true prophetes, and theyr doctrine that they taught, ſound and agreable to the will and worde of God: which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not, but neglected: &amp; therefore our wont full and former myrthe, was turned into ſorow and care then, vyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly bewailing our poore ſtate, led in captiuity: bicauſe we had no knowlege
<pb facs="tcp:26461:21"/>
and for not regardyng the lawe of the Lorde of hoſtes,<note place="margin">Eſay, 5,</note> but blaſphemynge the woorde of the holye one of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Baru, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> and for forſaking the fountain of wiſedom: wherin if we had ſtyll walked, vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly we had dwelte in reſt vppon the earthe: Then famiſhed oure ſoules for want of the liuely foode of gods ſacred word:<note place="margin">Amos 8,</note> but better had it bene for vs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue knowen the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, then after we knew it,<note place="margin">2, Peter, 2</note> to turn as we dyd from the holy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment geuen vnto vs: whyche then we paſſed not for, we vnderſtoode not the worthineſſe thereof, we knew not that by vertue therof, we had health, peace &amp; plenty: we knew not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruer of vs, and our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, from our enemies: we knew not howe precious a iewell it was, and how ſwete a refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing to our hungry ſoules, til we hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gred and thyrſted for it, and coulde not haue it, but in ſteede thereof, were fed and crammed wyth the moſte deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Antichriſtian foode of Rome, wherein was no ſmacke or taſte, no heauenly ſweteneſſe, no ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte, but rather bytterneſſe and ranke
<pb facs="tcp:26461:22"/>
poiſon, corrupting both body and ſoule: and therfore at thoſe dayes, mighte we iuſtly by wofull experience ſaye, where the preachers of gods word fayle, there periſh the people:<note place="margin">Prou, 25,</note> for then periſhed the poore ſelye flocke for want of the good ſhephardes,<note place="margin">Iohn, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0,</note> which had geuen their life for their ſhepe: and we poore wretches ſtraying and wandryng ſhepherdles, were in daunger of euerye wolfe and bloudye ſhepebyter, lefte as outcaſtes, and as a people forſaken, voyde of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, without hope, without helpe, ſaue onely at the handes of our omnipotent god, the great ſhephard. To whom we were then forced to flye, as to our onely refuge: Then beganne we to beholde the frailtye of our wicked nature: then conſidered we the heauy diſpleaſure of god, who for our vnthankfulnes had ſo louingly corrected vs: and of whom in the time of our proſperitie we wee moſt forgetfull, not regarding hym, tyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng rocked in the cradell of care, and as it were in manner ouerwhelmed with the waues of aduerſitie and ſourges of ſorrowe, whiche then cauſed vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe oure wickednes, and to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:26461:22"/>
the eternall God to be our onely helpe: Thenne called we to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce the ſweete bleſſynges of God whiche we in the triumphante tyme of the goſpell had receiued: and for neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whereof, we had now felt and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the bytterneſſe of hys diſpleaſure, who yet more mercifully and louingly delte with vs, then oure deſerte deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Then beganne we with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dygall chylde, to retourne from the ſwyne troughe, and ſubmytte oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the handes of our heauenlye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thenne cryed we, Lorde delyuer vs frome the tyrannous and merciles bloudye broode, that dailye perſecute thy people. Then cryed we, lorde laye to thy handes, for thy ennemies haue deſtroyed thy lawe: Then deſyred we the Lorde to delyuer vs, and releaſe vs oute of the extreame bondage and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, wherein we were miſerablye wrapped: and to bee reſtored to oure former fredome and libertye: whereof thorough our vnthankfulnes we were diſpoſſeſſed: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſought we the lord that his worde mighte once agayne be
<pb facs="tcp:26461:23"/>
a lanterne to oure feete, and that we mighte once agayne walke accordyng to his holy lawes. Thus in the trouble ſome and tyrannous time of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the chiefeſt of oure calamitie and miſerye (ſuche was then oure ſonge.) Thys canne God doe, and this woorke had god wroughte to make his forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children knowe hym, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee myndefull of the greate and mercifull kyndneſſe of ſo gratious a lorde. Oh bleſſed, ye twiſe bleſſed and happye were we that it thus pleaſed oure heauenly father, to laye his croſſe vppon vs, whiche doubtleſſe is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye for the Chriſtian ſoule as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall foode for the bodye: it made vs knowe hym, whome before thoroughe oure frailtye we hadde forgotten, and cauſed vs to humble our ſelues to him, in whoſe handes our onely helpe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, who then of hys endeleſſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and whoſe mightye mercye was ſuche, ſeeyng that in oure heartes we wer turned vnto hym, &amp; beholding our inwarde and hartye repentaunce for ſo greuouſly offendyng his diuine maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye: of his vnſpeakable loue, moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:26461:23"/>
and louinglye tendring vs, as the father his children, had then compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon vs, and turned his fauourable countenance towardes vs: and though for a while he had ſuffred vs to be euill entreated thorough tyrauntes,<note place="margin">Pſal, 107,</note> whome he vſed as inſtrumentes of his wrath, to corrcet vs, yet lo, at the laſt he harde the mournyng voices of vs poore cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyues, and helped vs oute of miſerye, and ſhewed himſelfe to bee as he is, a mighty god of mercy, and euen the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſtrengthe of his people,<note place="margin">Pſalm, 28,</note> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the healthe of his annointed: which he wonderfully declared, when we beyng in our chiefe diſtreſſe, thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſlauerye to them that dailye purſued vs: Then he in twincklyng of an eye by his mightye power deliuered vs from that miſerable bondage, out of that troubleſome and dreadefull ſea of ſorrowe wherein we were, euen as he did the children of Iſraell, through the red ſea from the euill Pharao, whome with all his trayne, in their chiefeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie, as God by his omnipotente power in the ſame ſea ouerwhelmed and drouned: So hath he likewiſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſlye
<pb facs="tcp:26461:24"/>
ouerthrowne oure enemies: who in theyr chiefeſte pryde, he hathe ſmyten downe beefore oure faces: and plaged theym that hated vs,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> * and put the lying lyppes to ſilence, whiche cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellye diſdaynfullye, and deſpighteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye reſyſted the truthe of God. Thys meruelous worke hathe our almightye God wrought and broughte to paſſe by hys electe and choſen ſeruaunte, and handmayden, our moſt gratious quene Elizabeth: God I ſaye the worker, and ſhe the inſtrument, whome God hadde rayſed euen as it were from the graue, to ouerthrow his and her enemies, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che by all poſſible meanes moſt trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſought her ouerthrow, deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and death. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god that deliuered Peter forth of priſon, &amp; by whoſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the chaines wherein he was bound fel from him:<note place="margin">Actes, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> and before whom the iron gates opened of their own accord, that Peter might eſcape the handes of his ennemies, woulde haue the Romiſhe Herodes vnderſtande, that there is no priſon or forte of that force, nor tower of ſuche terror, or keeper of ſuche cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie
<pb facs="tcp:26461:24"/>
and circumſpection, that can holde or kepe captiue thoſe whome God wil haue at libertie. Well, nowe hath Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith through Gods aſſiſtance, cut of the head of Holofernes, the ſiege is raiſed, the ſouldiors beeyng fled, Iudith with the inhabitantes of Bethulia, ioyfully triumphe, praiſyng god for the victory. Thus hath our God, the lord of hoſtes diſappointed that butcherly and bloody broode of theyr miſcheuous purpoſe, which their wicked harts had imagined whoſe ſerpentlyke tongues ſtirred vp ſtryfe,<note place="margin">Pſalm, 14</note> and vnder whoſe flatterynge lyppes lay hydde the poiſon of adders, and hath deliuered vs from their tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, euen as the byrde from the foulers ſnare, and hathe defaced their abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable wicked and Romiſh hipocriticall deuiſes, and diſplaced theyr falſe and lotheſome goddes of woode and ſtone. And of hys myghtye mercy hathe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored his woorde vnto vs, which plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifully is taughte and preached vnto vs, by thoſe whiche are ſpronge out of the aſhes of them, that with fyre were conſumed: by whome alſo the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes
<pb facs="tcp:26461:25"/>
are dulie and trulye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred: Nowe haue we for chaffe, corne, for darkenes, lyght, for ranke poyſon (a preſeruatiue) euen the bleſſed word of God, to heale vs from deſtruction, hys holy worde, I ſay, the liuely foode and pretious preſeruatiue of oure ſoules, whiche hath brought vs quietnes with forreyne enemyes, &amp; domeſtical peace, plenty health and al thyngs neceſſary. Oh, how mercifully hath the Lord delt with vs, that of myſerable bond ſlaues, in myſery, in darkenes, and in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of death, hath made vs free men to haue &amp; vſe the libertye and freedome of our conſcience, which is a treaſure of treaſures. Now hath god comforted vs after the tyme that he punyſhed, &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs, and for the yeares wherein we haue ſuffered aduerſity, he hath ſhewed vnto vs hys mercy, and to our children hys glory: Oh that men woulde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prayſe the goodneſſe of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal, 107,</note> and the wonders, that he doth for the children of men, who of hys mere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath deliuered vs from thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and ſpoyled vs, and were to ſtrong for vs, and hath ſatyſfied the emptye
<pb facs="tcp:26461:25"/>
ſoule, and fylled the hungry ſoule with good: wherefore my good brethren, as oure mercyfull and gratious God hath ſo done hys maruelous woorkes, that they ought to be had in remembraunce, &amp; as in the day of our trouble, we called vpon the Lord for helpe, who hath now deliuered vs, &amp; geuen vs our hartes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt: ſo ſhould we likewyſe now, with earneſt hearts &amp; willyng myndes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that, which we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promyſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God, which was amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and newneſſe of life, which I har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely wyſhe and deſyre of God may be, &amp; the which alſo the Lord doth loke for at oure handes, and he will not be mocked with all: But alas, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, I ſee rather a forgetfulneſſe in our ſelues, and ſynne and wickedneſſe, rather moſt ſhamefully to abound, then any amendmente of lyfe or reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of oure wycked manners. What pryde what whoredome, what theft, what, dronkenneſſe, what blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye and ſwearyng, what vſurye, what gredye and vnſatiable couetouſneſſe, what vntrue dealyng, is daylye vſed? no regarde of woorde or promyſe, no
<pb facs="tcp:26461:26"/>
ſkante the bondes or hande writynges with ſeale vppon ſeale is auaylable or ſufficient, without trauais in the lawe, and expence of money: Sinne I ſaye is made but a ſporte, for pryde is accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for cleanlines, whoredome, for a pange of youthe, thefte, a ſhifter, the drunkard a good companion, the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſwearer, a luſtye courtier, the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye couetuous vſurer, a ware thriuyng manne, the vntrue and ſubtyll dealer, pregnaunt and fyne wytted. Thus ſynne is accoumpted none offence, and as it appeareth, there is neyther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde or care, for the puniſhmente of the magiſtrate, nor feare of the plage of God for the ſame. But my brethern, do not theſe abhominable, filthye, and corrupte thynges whiche ſtynke before the face of GOD, and declare that we thynke in oure heartes there is no god. Shall we dwell in the tabernacle of the Lorde, or reſte vpon his holy hyll, that lyue thus careleſly, carnallye, and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly? (No) but he that leadeth an vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte lyfe, that dothe the thynge that is righte, and ſpeaketh the truthe from hys harte, that vſeth no deceyte in hys
<pb facs="tcp:26461:26"/>
tongue, and dothe no yll to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but perfourmeth that he promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vnto hym, and that ſetteth not by the vngodly: but maketh much of them that feare the Lorde: that geueth not hys money vppon vſurye, nor taketh rewarde againſt the innocent: and that in all theyr doynges haue the feare of the Lorde before their eyes. And theſe bee they that GOD wyll bleſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earthe, and in the worlde to come, they ſhalbe partakers of eternall glorye.</p>
            <p>But howe groweth this careleſnes and impudencye of lyfe amongeſt vs, which nowe ſo ſhamefully aboundeth? Truely thoroughe neglectyng to heare the woorde of God preached, and not beleuynge it, when we haue harde it: whiche when we hadde not, thenne we hungred for it, and nowe that it hathe pleaſed God to geue it agayne vnto vs, we begynne agayne not to care for yt: But my bretherne, be not ſo vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the greate benefyte of GOD. Conſyder, bee myndefull and thynke vppon the dolefull dayes paſſed, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gette not the terribleneſſe thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:27"/>
remember I ſay, the manifolde Godlye admonitions and warnynges: for the amendement of our wicked &amp; diſſolute lyfe, in the laſte tyme of the Goſpell, the great myſerye, and pitefull plages that were pronounced and foreſhewed by the electe miniſters of Ieſu Chriſte to come vpon vs, onles then ſpedye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce and amendement: But how littel regarded we the ſame, til crueltye had catched vs and that the flame of fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye faggottes flewe aboute oure eares. Let not therefore that merciles and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranous tyme, (the ſmarte whereof ſo latelye felte) be already forgotten, but let the ſame rather prouoke and moue vs lyke Chriſtians, to geue better hede now vnto the ſwete leſſons, Godly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, and daylye warnynges of Gods meſſangers, whiche he of his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng kyndnes and greate mercye hath thus once agayne ſente amongeſt vs, to declare hys will vnto vs: who dayly cry out, repentaunce, repentaunce, in the Lordes name: who moſt louyngly and fatherly, pityeth our deſtruction, if his warnyng may helpe, whiche alas, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth nothyng as appeareth: For we
<pb facs="tcp:26461:27"/>
are as ill, naye rather worſe, then wee wer before: but my brethren, if ye be ſo careleſſe that ye reſpect not the ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and fatherly warnynges of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye, pronounced by hys electe and choſen miniſters: Yet be not ſo diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe deſperate, ſo lyghtly to regard the maruelous and ſtraunge doinge and worke of the Lord hymſelf: euen the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty, who trulye is not pleaſed, but hyghly offended with oure heathenyſhe manners: wherof let the fearefull fyer from heauen, whiche ſo ſodenly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that huge and myghty monument and temple of Poules (be witneſſe) and let the ſundrye ſtraunge procreation &amp; monſtrous ſhape as well of children, as alſo of beaſtes (beare recorde) of oure monſtrous and beaſtly lyfe: remember alſo the verye heauens, heauily bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng our wo and miſery to come, whoſe late daily droppyng ſhowres, dolefully preached vnto vs the heauye wrathe of god, for our wickednes to be at hand, ye hanging ouer our heads, onleſſe betime we turne vnto the lord what chriſtian conſcience quaketh not to thynke vpon the premyſſes, turne therfore, and lette
<pb facs="tcp:26461:28"/>
amendement of life appeare in tyme, or els to heauy will the burdeyns bee for vs to beare, whyche God for oure diſobedience and wickednes wil lay v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs: I therfore exhort you for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake, that for as muche as in oure conuerſation and liuing we haue ſwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued from god, therby deſeruynge his heauie wrathe and diſpleaſure: ſo we may endeuor our ſelues tenne times to turne agayne and ſeeke the lorde euen from the bottome of our heartes with wepyng, faſtyng, and prayeng: and for as muche as nothyng is better than to feare God, and nothyng ſweter than to haue a reſpecte vnto the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the lord,<note place="margin">Syrach. 23</note> let vs be meke and lowely to heare the woorde of god, the gladde tidynges of Ieſu Chriſte prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and not ſlacke to beleeue it. * For where no knowledge of gods woorde is,<note place="margin">Syrach. 5 Prouer. 15</note> the ſoule is not well: and vayne are all thoſe, in whome no knowledge of god is. Let vs therfore take hede to our ſelues,<note place="margin">Sapi, 22</note> and keepe well our ſoules, that we forget not the thinges that our eies haue ſene: let our lyuyng bee agreable vnto the doctrine whiche we profeſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:26461:28"/>
that we geue not the ennemies of the Lorde, a cauſe to raile: for happy is he that readeth, and they that heare the worde of god, and kepe thoſe thynges that are written therin:<note place="margin">Reuela, 1,</note> and otherwiſe we are but ſlanderers of the goſpelle. And therfore let vs take away our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thoughtes out of the ſight of God, ceaſe to doo euill, ſeke iudgement, help the poore oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Eſay, 1.</note> be fauorable to the fatherles, defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> widow, &amp; then ſhal our ſinnes as red as ſcarlet, be made as white as ſnow: and then as God of his mightifull mercy hath brought downe and ſuppreſſed the ſtoute mountaynes and hygh rockes,<note place="margin">Baruch. 5. Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 17.</note> the ennemyes of hys truthe, whiche maintained theyr owne welthines with oppreſſion, and who al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo haue long bene glad and reioyſed at our late decaye, ſo ſhal he likewiſe force them (whoſe ioye is nowe turned to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſtill to mourne in theyr owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and we ſhall encreaſe and not diminiſhe, but ſtyll quietlye inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite enioy and peaceablye poſſeſſe oure ſwete &amp; bleſſed land y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floweth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> milke &amp; hony, which god hath geuen vs to our vnſpeakable comforte and the greate
<pb facs="tcp:26461:29"/>
glorye of oure almighty &amp; heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: with whome after this tranſitorye life ended, we ſhalbee partakers of hys heauenly kingdome. To that immortal god therfore, with his only ſonne, oure ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte, and to the holye ghoſt, that ſwete comforter, be al praiſe and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis ꝙ I. S.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>
               <hi>A praier or geuing of thankes</hi> for our deliuery, from the hands of our enemies, &amp; reſtoryng vnto vs the fredom of our conſcience.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt puiſaunt mighty and euerliuing God, the god of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the comforter of the comfortles, the hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per vp of ſuch as were fallen, the mercifull &amp; free forgeuer of the penitent ſinners, we ſorowfull and ſinfull wretches, thy poore and ſely creatures, acknowledge &amp; confeſſe our greuous offences, ye we proteſt before thy maieſtye againſt our
<pb facs="tcp:26461:29"/>
ſelues, our diſobedience, our abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble deteſtable and wicked ſinnes, which we moſt greuouſly againſt thy diuyne maieſtie haue committed, in tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng thy holy commaundements, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting thy ſacred word, and deſpiſyng the godly admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and warnings of thy miniſters, the preachers &amp; teachers of the ſame, (for the whiche) oure moſte heynous and horrible crime, as of thy iuſte iuſtice it pleaſed thee to take from vs, and worthily to diſpoſſeſſe vs of that heauenly treaſure &amp; ineſtimable dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the onely ſubſtaunce of our ſoules thy liuely and euerlaſting worde, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough want wherof we daily decayed, pitifully periſhed, and grewe more and more into ſundry and manifolde miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ye bothe we and oure countrey in daunger of vtter deſtruction, till of thy only goodnes, and heauenly clemency: according to the multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and not of our deſert, turning thy face from our ſinnes, forgetting our vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthines and rather carefully pitieng our wofull and miſerable ſtate it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the agayne to reſtore vnto vs the fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of oure conſcience: and in time to
<pb facs="tcp:26461:30"/>
lay to thy hande for the defence of thy people againſt their enemies, who tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough their viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce had oppreſſed their flock, and troden thy truth vnder foote and diddeſt delyuer vs from the raging madneſſe and tyranny of that mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyleſſe, gredy, rauenous, and Romyſhe bloudſuckers, euen as thou by thy myghtie power delyueredſt Danyell foorth of the den from the hungry ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, therby cuttyng our ſacke of ſorow in peces, turning our miſery to mirth, our woe to wealth, and clothynge vs with ioye and gladneſſe, and haſte alſo gathered together the remnant of thy flocke diſperſed in ſundry countreys to feede nowe with vs, togyther, vppon the holſome pleaſant and ſwete paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of thy ſacred word, here in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, bleſſed, and fruitfull countreye of Englande, which we through thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpekable and great mercy, to the praiſe of thy holy name and our comfort, doo quietly and peaſibly poſſeſſe: So nowe muſte gratious and eternall God, and heauenly father, we ſelye wretches of our ſelues moſte vyle and voyde of all goodneſſe, without thy aſſiſtaunce and
<pb facs="tcp:26461:30"/>
fatherly care for vs, proſtratyng oure ſelues before thy maieſtie, do with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained harts moſt humbly beſeche thee that this cherefull lyght of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may continually ſhyne vpon vs and our contrey: and that it may pleaſe thee more &amp; more to poure out thy holy ſpirite vppon vs, that by the aſſiſtance therof, wee maye bee folowers of the ſwete &amp; comfortable doctrin now daily pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced &amp; taught by thyn elect &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen miniſters, &amp; neuer herafter go back agayn, nor fall from thy truth, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, &amp; ſtil go forward in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our profeſſion, that our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous life may be an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſinners may be conuerted vnto thee: be ſtil fauorable O'lord, be now &amp; euer a defence vnto thy people of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, &amp; els where ſoeuer thy goſpell is taught, and let no more thy heritage of England be brought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion: geue vs no more ouer, nor ſuffer vs neuer hereafter to be a reprofe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, neither ſuffer any more ſuche as be ſtrangers to thy truth to gouerne vs, that the blood of innocentes be no more ſpilt: but good lorde for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye ſake, mollyfie the ſtony heartes of
<pb facs="tcp:26461:31"/>
thoſe wilful ones that in time they may mekely taſt the ſweetenes of thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goſpel, learne to know the, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the number of the flocke of thy folde: that we may be glad and reioice at their conuerſion but if they ſhal ſtill frowardly &amp; obſtinately perſiſt in their wilfull and wicked blyndnes, deſpiſe thy holy lawes, diſdain the truthe, cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly contende, and rebelliouſly reſiſte the godly religious procedinges of our moſte gratious and ſoueraign princeſſe quene Elizabeth, to whom we humbly beſech thee to graunt a long, ioiful, and proſperous raign, to the more magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and extolling of thy glorious name and the comforte of this thy realme and people of England, by thee committed vnto her gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: &amp; whom alſo thou haſte appointed, and by thy holy worde autoriſed chiefe and ſupreme gouernor. Then lord we pray the and reuerently requeſte thee, as thou arte an ennemye to the wicked doers, abhorreſt the bloud thyrſtye and deceitefull, and broughte their pomp and power to noughte: So let their wickednes fal vpon their own heades, and poure out thy indignacion
<pb facs="tcp:26461:31"/>
vpon them, that they may periſhe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our ſyght, to their vtter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and neuer more be able to ryſe vp nor rebell agaynſt thee and thy Chriſt, nor preuail againſt or moleſt thy flock: but be thou our heauenly ſhepard, euer in the myddeſt of vs, that we alwayes may, beyng as one flocke of one folde, drawynge together by one lyne, with godly and zelous hartes, chriſtianlike profeſſyng one truthe, euen thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goſpell, and plentifully yeldynge foorth the fruites of the ſame, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually receiue thy heuenly venedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vppon vs, and our contrey: that our paſtures may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ne, and the earthe bryng foorthe and yelde her encreaſe: that in due tyme we may with thankes geuynge, reape and gather the fruites therof to our comfort, ioyfully making our boaſt of thy praiſe, and all the dais of our lyfe ſerue thee (our Lord &amp; God) in holineſſe and rightuouſneſſe. To whom with the ſonne and the holy ghoſt, one onely and eternall God, bee all praiſe, glorye and maieſtie for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26461:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don by Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Sutton for Edward Sutton dwellyng in Lumbarde ſtrete at the ſigne of the Cradell. The .xxi. day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, in the yere of our Lorde 1562.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peruſed and allovved according to the Quenes maieſties iniunctions.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
